<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>micahlerner.com</title>
    <link>http://www.micahlerner.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on micahlerner.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2016 22:48:31 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.micahlerner.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The first computer that almost changed the world</title>
      <link>http://www.micahlerner.com/posts/osborne/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2016 22:48:31 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.micahlerner.com/posts/osborne/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;While at my favorite independent bookstore, &lt;a href=&#34;www.keplers.com&#34;&gt;Kepler’s&lt;/a&gt; in Menlo Park, I discovered a jewel of geekiness. The book in question is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Core-Memory-Visual-Vintage-Computers/dp/0811854426&#34;&gt;Core Memory: A History of Vintage Computers&lt;/a&gt;, and I thought it would be interesting to query my parents about some of the computing relics detailed in the book. I was quite surprised to learn that not only were some of the computers used by my parents, but that several might be stashed in our attic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this discovery in hand, I embarked on an odyssey into the dark reaches of my attic. (This is not hyperbole as you can see from the following picture.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.micahlerner.com/assets/osborne/atticodyssey.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The attic&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lo and behold, what did I find in the dark, dusty, and dreary recesses? Nothing less than two, TWO, original &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Osborne_1&#34;&gt;Osborne computers&lt;/a&gt; amid some precariously piled file cabinets. As I lugged them downstairs, the cogs inside my head were already spinning at the thought of exposing a whole new generation to old technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-osborne-and-what-did-they-make&#34;&gt;What Is Osborne and what did they make?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Osborne_Computer_Corporation&#34;&gt;Osborne&lt;/a&gt; was a computer company founded by two young entrepreneurs in 1980. Adam Osborne and Lee Felsenstein combined their mind power to create computers that were not just personal, but portable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They faced the obstacle of transitioning from computing monoliths that took up whole levels of office space to (relatively) luggable computers that could fit under a plane seat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-the-osborne-1&#34;&gt;About the Osborne 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their first product was named the Osborne 1, and sold for an initial price of $1,795 (around $4,700 adjusted for inflation), meaning that it was at least relatively accessible to the general public. The Osborne 1 was the first computer to come bundled with applications, a pioneering idea at the time. All together, the software would have cost around $1,500 ($4,000 adjusted for inflation) by itself. However, the design was not entirely original. The look borrowed heavily from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xerox_NoteTaker&#34;&gt;Xerox Notetaker&lt;/a&gt;, yet Xerox’s product was simply a prototype and not a production model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.micahlerner.com/assets/osborne/osbornedesc.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The Osborne 1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-impressions&#34;&gt;First Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first look, I didn’t know what to think of this old computer. I had passed by it multiple times in the attic, albeit in previous years. My interest was piqued by my reading of the vintage computer book I had picked up, and now I felt confident that I could get it working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While trying to muscle it down the stairs, I did bump it into the wall more than once. Yet this old sack of potatoes wouldn’t die, even after I semi-dropped it onto the floor. After plugging it in, and booting it up, all I could feel was excitement. I had been daydreaming about the moment of truth for a minimum of two weeks, and now it was here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I pushed, or shoved more like it, the floppy into the drive, the dust began rising. Being the neatfreak that I am, I decide to put a towel under the computer, so as not to get my carpet dirty. In the pictures, you can probably see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reaching around to the back, the switch was flicked, and the screen glimmered to life. My arm pump was cut short by a buzzing sound, followed by a long string of multiplying “BOOT ERROR”. The computer screeched at me. And glowed bright red? Was the computer broken? I considered the possibilities. It had been ravaged in an earthquake, it had been destroyed in a flood, it had overheated and taken a permanent vacation. I was feeling adventurous, and the excitement still hadn’t worn off. I put in another disk. The screeching seemed louder. I put in a different disc. Same deal. I flipped the floppy over, and reinserted, trying every combination. Upside down. Sideways. Upside down and sideways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I repeated this with five different floppies. It still didn’t work. What wasn’t I doing right? At this point I realized that I had committed a newbie error. From the pictures you probably can’t see it, but there is a latch that you have to flip down over the end of the floppy. I flipped it down, and it worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This experience characterized my learning to use the obscenely complicated Osborne. Try, read the manual, try again. I don’t even want to know what this meant for people “back in the day”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cool-what-is-the-technology-behind-it&#34;&gt;Cool, What is the technology behind it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Osborne 1 came bundled with around 10 programs, yet the number varied depending on when the computer was purchased (Seeing that more software was designed as time went on, this makes sense.) At the time of sale, the included programs were some of the best in their respective areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consequently, most of their ideas were copied and are prevalent in computers today. For example: the idea of file extensions (.doc, .txt, .jpg) came from distinguishing between the items on this computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.micahlerner.com/assets/osborne/osborneyada.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The Osborne 1, opened&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the operating system was incompatible with others of the time, it was not a problem. Osborne Computer Company made sure that all of the frequently executed business tasks were covered by programs pre-packaged with the Computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.micahlerner.com/assets/osborne/cpandm.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;CP/M&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The package would be named &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CP/M&#34;&gt;CP/M&lt;/a&gt; or Control Program/Monitor (or Control Program for Microcomputers) and it would run many approved programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The list was as follows:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WordStar (think Microsoft Word…in a terminal format. I tried hard to figure this out, which I eventually did, however you must memorize many commands and shortcuts for the program to be efficient.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SuperCalc (a precursor to Excel)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CBasic/MBasic (BASIC: a basic programming language)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dBase II (database management software made by Ashton Tate (which turned into Borland, another of my dad’s employers)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Ledger Programs (3 programs that are awesome and entertaining. Pie Graphs in a terminal.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Colossal Cave (first adventure computer game: download it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ifarchive.org/if-archive/games/pc/advbds.zip&#34;&gt;here for PC&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ifarchive.org/if-archive/games/pc/advos2.zip&#34;&gt;here for Mac&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ifarchive.org/if-archive/games/source/advqnx.tar.gz&#34;&gt;here for Linux systems&lt;/a&gt;. The downloads are slow, so don’t be too impatient.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deadline (one of the first mystery detective games)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guessed that WordStar had received the most use by the users of the Osborne 1, so I thought it would be interesting to attempt first. Getting the “simple” WordStar to work meant I had to call in the big guns, my father.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Dad? How the heck do you do this?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, I caught a lucky break. Not only did my Dad remember most of the commands, but he knew how to read the manual. When we got over that first hump, I wanted to type something by myself. The commands were so arcane that I had to type 5 characters just to make something bold. Think about that. Additionally, there is no specific “Delete” key, just a left backspace. Everything about the word processor was so mind-numbing and tediously repetitive that I would have produced a draft on a typewriter more quickly. Once again, I felt a tinge of pity for the individuals who had to actually slog through the manuals.  Yet, this experience did not detract from my adrenaline rush of actually getting it to work. Obviously, pretty Graphical User Interfaces had made me jaded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Core Memory noted, selling of all of the programs separately would have cost more to the consumer than the computer itself. Packaging functionality like WordStar was a move that helped establish the Osborne 1 as the premier choice in its class, until the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Compaq&#34;&gt;competitors&lt;/a&gt; caught on. It was a technical marvel that all of this could run on a computer with so little in the way of electronic endowment. The specifications of the Osborne computer are below - the size of the resources meant that there was little allowed in the way of programming efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.micahlerner.com/assets/osborne/specs.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Specs&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Specifications:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;20.5 inches wide, 14.5 inches deep, and 8.5 inches high&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Processor-Z80A, 4MHz CPU clock&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Memory size-64K bytes programmable (RAM), 4K read-only memory bank-switched and 60K of programmable memory available for software (You couldn’t even type half a page in Vista with 64k)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5-inch display&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;69-key detachable keyboard, full-travel sloped keytops includes 12-key numeric keypad!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power on-off switch in rear, Reset pushbutton on front panel, Brightness and contrast controls on front panel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Program Execution Speed: Program in read-only memory executes without delay, Programmable memory adds average delay times as follows: first Ml cycle-188 nsec, Subsequent consecutive Ml cycles-0 sec, Non-Ml cycles-375 nsec&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Osborne Computer Company made a series of mistakes. Under mounting competition and demand, Adam Osborne boasted about new products that hadn’t been released yet, in addition to pointing out that they would be better than the Osborne 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Customers canceled their pending buys of Osborne 1’s in anticipation of the new release, however this caused OCC to begin bleeding money. By September 13, 1983 (24 years and 3 days ago from when this article was posted) the company had declared Chapter 11 Bankruptcy. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theregister.co.uk/2005/06/20/no_osborne_effect_at_osborne/&#34;&gt;Some argue that tales of Osborne’s demise have been exaggerated&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>